<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the Right Honourable, the Lord Mayor, Alderman and citizens of London, at S. Mary-le-Bow on the fifth of November, 1680 by William Cave ...</title>
            <author>Cave, William, 1637-1713.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 59 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A31428</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1606</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1491</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12265116</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12265116</idno>
            <idno type="VID">58010</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A31428)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 58010)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 911:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the Right Honourable, the Lord Mayor, Alderman and citizens of London, at S. Mary-le-Bow on the fifth of November, 1680 by William Cave ...</title>
                  <author>Cave, William, 1637-1713.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 35 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by M. White, for R. Chiswel ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Acts XVII, 6 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:58010:1"/>
            <opener>
               <signed>Ward Mayor.</signed>
               <date>
                  <hi>Martis nono die Novemb.</hi> 1680. <hi>Anno<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Regni Regis Caroli ſecundi, Angliae, &amp;c. xxxii.</hi>
               </date>
            </opener>
            <p>UPon the motion of Sr. <hi>Thomas Aleyn,</hi> Knight and Baronet, and Alderman, now made unto this Court, This Court doth deſire Dr. <hi>Cave</hi> to print his Sermon preached at <hi>Bow-Church,</hi> on the Fifth inſtant, being the Anniverſary day of Thankſgiving for Deliverance from the <hi>Gun-Powder-Treaſon</hi> Plot, before the Lord Mayor, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermen and Citizens of this City.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Wagſtaffe.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:58010:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached before the Right HONOURABLE THE Lord Mayor, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermen and Citizens of LONDON, At S. <hi>MARY-LE-BOW</hi> on the <hi>Fifth</hi> of <hi>Novem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> MDCLXXX. By <hi>William Cave,</hi> D. D. Chaplain in Ordinary to His Majeſty, and Rector of <hi>Great Allhallows, London.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Origen. contra Celſ. lib. 3. p. 115.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>M. White,</hi> for <hi>R. Chiſwel</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Roſe</hi> and <hi>Crown</hi> in S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard. 1680.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:58010:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58010:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Right Honourable S<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> Patience VVard LORD MAYOR of the City of LONDON, And to the Court of ALDERMEN.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>VVHen I firſt engaged in this ſervice, I did it with ſome reluctancy, not out of any un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willingneſs to the thing it ſelf, but the conſciouſneſs of mine own unfitneſs for
<pb facs="tcp:58010:3"/>it. And when I receiv'd the commands of your Court for the Publication, I found in my ſelf a greater reluctancy; not that I knew any thing in the Sermon that fear'd the light, but becauſe I had ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom ſeen printing of Sermons attain the deſired effect, being generally thrown aſide, and the moſt uſeful and innocent diſcourſes oftner entertain'd with ſpite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and diſingenuous reflections, than im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved to the real purpoſes of Religion. But in this I over-rul'd my ſelf, leſt I ſhould ſeem to contemn Authority, while I am profeſſedly pleading for obedience to it. If any thing herein may miniſter to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lic uſe, confirm men the more in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion, and awaken an honeſt and prudent care againſt thoſe, whoſe principles and practices, as well as their intereſts, naturally tend to deſtroy our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and to diſturb our quiet (eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb facs="tcp:58010:3"/>that of this great and honourable Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſo intolerable an eyeſore to them) if it may attain theſe ends, 'tis the utmoſt that can be hoped for from the mean endeavours of</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
               <signed>Your moſt Faithful and Obedient Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, William Cave.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:58010:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:58010:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ACT. xvii. 6.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Theſe that have turned the world upſide down, are come hither alſo.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>SO inveterate are the prejudices of Educati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſo prevalent and uncontroulable the force of a long preſcription, that tho' there had been nothing elſe to encounter, Chriſtianity was ſure at its firſt ſetting out to meet with a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous oppoſition both from <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles.</hi> The Gentile-world combin'd their whole power againſt it, and ſet themſelves to run it down, as a novel and an upſtart Sect, that came to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine their ancient Religion, that had ſo long go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern'd the minds of men. But none purſued it with ſo fierce and implacable a malice as the <hi>Jews,</hi> who having been for ſeveral ages trained up in an unmeaſurable reverence and veneration for the Moſaic inſtitutions, thought themſelves deeply concern'd to make head againſt that Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, whoſe avow'd deſign it was to abrogate their whole Temple-miniſtration; <hi>and to change the cuſtomes that</hi> Moſes <hi>delivered.</hi> Upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count having imbrued their hands in the blood of its Founder, and treated him with all the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:58010:5"/>of contempt and cruelty, they reſolved to follow home the blow, and if poſſible, to ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh his Diſciples and Followers out of the world; whom therefore they ſought in all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, partly by open violence, partly by arts of falſhood and inſinuation to expoſe to the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the laws, and the rage of the multitude. And ſuch was the caſe of <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> in this Chapter, who being engaged in their Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical travels, were come down to <hi>Theſſalonica,</hi> the Metropolis of that part of <hi>Macedonia,</hi> where in the Jewiſh Synagogue S. <hi>Paul</hi> managed the cauſe of Chriſt with ſo much eloquence and ſtrength of reaſon, (<hi>ver.</hi> 2, 3.) that not a few of the <hi>Jews</hi> themſelves, but eſpecially vaſt numbers of the <hi>Greek</hi> proſelytes (who were not enſlaved to opinions and principles, to parties and intereſts) came over to him, <hi>ver.</hi> 4. But the Sun that melts the wax, hardens clay; his Sermons having a quite contrary effect upon the obſtinate unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving <hi>Jews,</hi> who not being able to reſiſt the clearneſs of his arguments, betook themſelves to force and clamour, the laſt refuges of an impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and a baffled cauſe. So gathering to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the refuſe of the common people, <hi>v.</hi> 5. they blew up the City into a tumult and uproar, and aſſaulted the houſe where the Apoſtles lodg'd: but miſſing them (who had prudently
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:58010:5"/>withdrawn themſelves) they ſeiz'd <hi>Jaſon</hi> the Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lord, and as many of the Chriſtians as they could meet with, and dragging them before the Magiſtrates of the City, loaded them with no leſs than conſpiracy and treaſon, crying out with a rude noiſe and clamour, Here are the men, that are the common incendiaries of all Countreys, that whereever they come, undermine the peace and proſperity of humane ſociety, that erect <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perium in imperio,</hi> a Kingdom contrary to the Laws and conſtitutions of the Roman Empire, and not content to have filled other places with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion and diſorder, are come here amongſt us to violate our peace, and embroil us in inteſtine feuds and quarrels, <hi>Theſe are the men, that having turn'd the world upſide down, are come hither alſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A heavy charge; and if true, enough to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parage the credit of any Religion in the world. But thanks be to God the charge in this caſe was as falſe and groundleſs, as the deſign of it was ſpiteful and malicious; the behaviour of theſe holy men having in all places been as harmleſs and inoffenſive, as the Doctrine they preacht was peaceable, and beneficial to the world; howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſome have ſince for very bad ends dreſt it up with another face, and made it look more like the fiery Doctrine of <hi>Mahomet,</hi> than that of our
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:58010:6"/>meek humble Saviour, the Doctrine of <hi>the Prince of peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In ſpeaking to theſe words, I ſhall do theſe three things,</p>
            <p>Firſt, Shew, that this has been an old charge upon Religion and the Profeſſors of it, to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbers of the publick peace.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That Chriſtianity is ſo far from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing juſtly obnoxious to this charge, that of all Religions it beſt ſecures the intereſts of civil Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and the peace of the world.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, I ſhall enquire whether there be any part of the Chriſtian Church at this day juſtly guilty of this charge.</p>
            <p n="1">I. It has been an old charge upon true Religion and the profeſſours of it, to be diſturbers of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick peace. For the enemy of all righteouſneſs knows no better way to render them obnoxious to Soveraign powers, than by repreſenting them as enemies to Government, and inconſiſtent with the proſperity of the Civil State. Princes are exquiſitely tender and jealous of their Crowns, and the bleſſings of public peace are infinitely dear and valuable to every honeſt and ſober man, ſo that it's no wonder if they be apt to look ſhy upon any thing, that has but the character of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:58010:6"/>and diſloyalty (tho' never ſo unjuſtly) ſtampt upon it. And this way has in all ages been found ſucceſsful. The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in <hi>Egypt</hi> had a hard hand kept over them, becauſe ſuſpected of attempts againſt the Government, and that under a pretence of Religion and worſhipping their own God, they would reſcue themſelves from the cruelties of the houſe of bondage. <hi>David</hi> was traduc'd to <hi>Saul</hi> as a Conſpirator againſt his Crown and dignity, and <hi>Elijah</hi> to <hi>Ahab</hi> as <hi>the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bler of Iſrael.</hi> The <hi>Chaldean</hi> Courtiers repreſented <hi>Daniel</hi> and his Companions as peeviſh oppoſers of the King's Proclamation. By the ſame artifice <hi>Haman</hi> laid a train to blow up the Jewiſh Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by telling <hi>Ahaſuerus,
<note place="margin">Eſth. 3.8.</note> they were a people that kept not the Kings Laws, and that therefore it was not for his profit to ſuffer them,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>a perverſe and unſociable generation,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ap. Joſeph. Antiquit. l.</hi> 11. <hi>c.</hi> 6. <hi>p.</hi> 375. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </note> (as that Emperours Edict repreſents them) <hi>an ill-natured people, croſs to the Laws, and diſobedient to their Princes, diſaffected to Monarchy, and the affairs of the Empire.</hi> No man ever gave greater demonſtrations of a juſt ſubmiſſion and deference to Authority than our bleſſed Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, and yet was himſelf arraign'd, condemn'd, and executed as <hi>an enemy unto Caeſar.</hi> How oft were his Apoſtles accus'd for being ring-leaders of a faction, men that talkt ſtrange words of <hi>one
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:58010:7"/>King Jeſus, and acted contrary to the decrees of Caeſar?</hi> And in the primitive times nothing more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon than to find the Heathens charging Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans to be traitors to the Government, and the peſts of humane ſociety, and that they were <hi>hoſtes humani generis,</hi> the common enemies of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid. Juſtin. Mart. Apol.</hi> 11. <hi>p.</hi> 58.</note> Nor could they under their bittereſt ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings ſo much as comfort one another with the promiſes of a Kingdom reſerv'd for them above, but the officers that over-heard them, immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly traduc't them to the Prince as ambitious affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors of the Empire.</p>
            <p>A calumny, than which nothing can be more abſurd and ſenſeleſs. For Religion, where 'tis not more pretended than practiſed,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Adv. Colot. p.</hi> 1125.</note> is (as <hi>Plutarch</hi> truly ſtiles it) the ligature of all Communities, and the ſecurity of Laws; and a City, ſayes he, may as well be built in the air without ground to ſtand on, as a State be either conſtituted or preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved without the ſupportment of Religion.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Orat. ad Aug. ap. Dion. in Vit. Aug. p.</hi> 490.</note> Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this account the great Stateſman <hi>Maecenas</hi> pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently adviſed <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, by all means and upon all occaſions to advance Religion and the worſhip of the gods, as the ſtrongeſt Bulwark againſt conſpiracy and treaſon. Nor is this founded only in the nature of Religion, but in the juſtice of the Divine Providence, which uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally rewards piety and vertue (eſpecially in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lic
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:58010:7"/>Societies) with peace and plenty, and a flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing ſtate and condition in this world. To which purpoſe <hi>Cicero</hi> layes it down as a maxim of State,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Omnia pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpera eveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt colenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Deos. Cicer. vid. de nat. deor. lib.</hi> 1.</note> That a people that have a care of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion muſt needs be proſperous, and can never be unhappy, till they become irreligious: and he tells us, that the arms and inſtruments, by which the <hi>Romans</hi> conquered the World, were not ſo much ſtrength and policy, as Religion and piety. And 'tis no more than what the Wiſe man obſerv'd long ſince,
<note place="margin">Prov. 14.34.</note> that 'tis <hi>righteouſneſs exalts a Nation, while ſin is the reproach of any people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. Chriſtianity is ſo far from being juſtly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious to this charge, that of all Religions it beſt ſecures the intereſts of civil authority, and the peace of the world. Which will be abundantly evident, if we conſider theſe three things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The expreſs and peremptory Laws, which Chriſt and his Apoſtles have given in this matter, commanding us in words as plain as words can tell us, to <hi>ſtudy to be quiet,</hi> to be <hi>humble</hi> and <hi>gentle,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 4.11. Rom. 12.18. Eph. 4.31. Rom. 14.49.</note> and <hi>as much as in us lies to live peaceably with all men, to put away ſtrife, and clamour, and evil ſpeaking,</hi> and <hi>to follow after the things that make for peace;</hi> to obey Rulers and Magiſtrates, to honour their perſons, revere their power, and quietly live under the protection of their Government, <hi>to give unto Caeſar
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:58010:8"/>the things that are Caeſars, as well as unto God the things that are Gods;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 13.1, 2.</note> that <hi>every ſoul be ſubject unto the higher powers, for that there is no power but of God, and that the powers that be are ordained of God, whoſoever therefore reſiſteth the power, reſiſteth the ordinance of God, and they that reſiſt, ſhall receive to themſelves damnation; therefore ye muſt needs be ſubject not only for wrath but alſo for conſcience ſake.</hi> Obſerve, <hi>let every ſoul,</hi> of what rank, quality, or degree ſoever, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſayes <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> upon theſe words, <hi>tho' thou art an Apoſtle, tho' an Evangeliſt, tho' a Prophet, or whatſoever thou art,</hi> thou muſt be ſubject: it being plain (ſayes he) that theſe things are commanded <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, not only to Laymen, but to Biſhops, to Prieſts, to Monks, Perſons under the ſevereſt diſcipline of Religion. A man that conſiders how careful this good Father is to bring the Clergy within the verge of this command, would be apt to think, he clearly foreſaw, and particularly ſet himſelf againſt the tyranny and uſurpations of the See of <hi>Rome.</hi> And indeed he has ſo fenc't it in, that, unleſs the Biſhop of that Church can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to be greater than Apoſtles, Evangeliſts or Prophets, there's no ſtarting-hole left for him to eſcape. But what ſpeak we of Apoſtles or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, when 'tis now for ſeveral ages notorious to the world, that <hi>he oppoſes and exalts himſelf above
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:58010:8"/>all that is called God, or is worſhipped,</hi> and has not ſcrupled to uſurp the very titles and royalties of God himſelf. And becauſe whatever power the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> pretend to, muſt be derived from S. <hi>Peter,</hi> let us in the next place enquire what di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection S. <hi>Peter</hi> himſelf gives us in this caſe, and we ſhall find that both the Apoſtle of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and the Doctor of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> write and ſpeak the ſame things, 1 Pet. 2.13, 14, 15. <hi>Submit your ſelves unto every ordinance of man for the Lords ſake; whether it be to the King as ſupreme, or unto Governours, as thoſe that are ſent by him, for the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of evil doers, and for the praiſe of them that do well; for ſo is the will of God,</hi> &amp;c. 'Tis a Law that has a peculiar ſtamp and ſignature of divine authority upon it. How far they who inſolent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly claim to be S. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Succeſſors, agree with this doctrine, we ſhall ſee by and by. But leſt men, who naturally love an unbridled liberty, ſhould take occaſion to forget this duty, S. <hi>Paul</hi> has made it a ſolemn and ſtanding part of the miniſterial office <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to be their <hi>Remembrancers</hi> in this caſe,
<note place="margin">Tit. 3.1.</note> 
               <hi>put them in mind to be ſubject to principalities and powers, and to obey Magiſtrates.</hi> Laſtly, Theſe commands thus plainly delivered, thus frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inculcated, are to be complyed with not only out of principles of fear, but of conſcience, and are bound upon us with the conſiderations of no
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:58010:9"/>leſs than eternal happineſs or miſery in the other world.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The true genius and ſpirit of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Religion is oppoſite to nothing more, than to diſturbance and diſorder; for 'tis a ſpirit of meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and humility, <hi>not thinking of our ſelves more highly than we ought to think, but in honour preferring one another;</hi> a ſpirit of love and gentleneſs, of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and integrity, that <hi>renders to all their dues, tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to whom tribute is due, cuſtome to whom cuſtome, fear to whom fear, honour to whom honour.</hi> Wherever Chriſtianity is cordially complyed with, it begets the moſt ſweet and benign, the moſt peaceable and benevolent temper of mind, repreſſes all ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty and indeliberate tranſports, and ſuffers not the mans ſpirit to be ruffled with paſſion by eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry trivial affront or injury that's offered to him. It enables us to be patient towards all men, and to bear provocations with a generous mind, to carry our ſelves towards thoſe that wrong us with all kindneſs and gentleneſs, and to be ready to do them all the good we can. 'Tis not enough that we do not fly out into the exceſſes of an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagant revenge, the Chriſtian ſpirit is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more, 'tis to treat our enemies with all the arts of ſoftneſs and good nature, to interpret their actions with candor and ingenuity, to love their perſons, though we condemn their vices,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:58010:9"/>to ſtudy their amendment, to pray for, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote (what in us lies) their comfort and quiet in this, and their happineſs in another world. It teaches us to be content with our place and ſtation, and to take up with that portion, which the wiſdom of the divine providence has allotted to us, levels pride and ambition, and makes us willing to abate of our own private intereſts, when it may conduce to the peace and proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the public: it naturally begets a mighty regard and reverence for Superiours, a dread of their power, a veneration for their authority, and a readineſs to ſacrifice our eſtates or lives for the common ſafety. This is the true life and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of Chriſtianity, and he that can be religious without this, muſt be a Chriſtian by a contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction. And therefore when the two <hi>ſons of thunder</hi> were hot in fetching down fire from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to be revenged upon thoſe Cities that would not entertain them, our Lord takes them up, and tells them,
<note place="margin">Luk. 9.55.</note> 
               <hi>you know not what manner of ſpirit you are of;</hi> you little conſider the nature and deſign of that Evangelical inſtitution, which I am come to ſet on foot in the world, ſuch paſſionate wild-fire as you breath after, does but little ſuit with the mild and gentle ſpirit of the Goſpel. The ſumm is this, Were men duly influenc't by the power of that Religion which they profeſs, the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:58010:10"/>world would ſoon be bleſſed with the moſt hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py ſcene and ſtate of things, Governours would rule peaceably and ſecurely, ſubjects obey freely and quietly, and every man in his capacity would be in ſome meaſure as happy and proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, as himſelf, or other men could make him. And that there was a time, when ſuch a ſpirit eminently rul'd in the breaſts of Chriſtians will appear, if we conſider,</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The temper and practice of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Chriſtians in the firſt and beſt ages of the Goſpel, when men really were what they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to be, when they liv'd and lov'd as bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, honoured even their Heathen Magiſtrates, paid their tributes, obey'd their laws, ſerv'd in their wars, and pray'd daily for their proſperity and ſafety. Such an inſtance of univerſal charity, modeſty, and obedience was our bleſſed Saviour, readily paying tribute, though it put him to the expence and charges of a miracle, freely owning <hi>Pilats</hi> authority to be from heaven, and cheerfully ſubmitting to his unrighteous ſentence: ſuch were his Apoſtles, who tho' unjuſtly ſcourg'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Council, gave not an ill word or look, but <hi>went away rejoycing;</hi> and when <hi>Herod</hi> had bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barouſly kill'd one of their number, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd the next day to ſend another of them the ſame way, what courſe did the Chriſtians take
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:58010:10"/>in this caſe? fire the City about his ears? hire a Ruffian to ſtab him, or a Phyſician to poyſon him? oh no, they oppos'd with nothing but prayer to Heaven.
<note place="margin">See <hi>Prim. Chriſt. Part III. chap.</hi> 3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4. where the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of the ancient Chriſtians in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is fully repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note> And the ſame were the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians in ſucceeding times, as I could ſhew at large, would the time; and your patience, give me leave. <hi>Tertullian</hi> aſſures us, That in their Church-ſervice they daily pray'd for, and in their conſtant practice promoted the happineſs and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity of the Empire; that the Chriſtian was an enemy to no man, and much leſs to his Prince; and both he and the reſt of the Chriſtian Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſts do upon all occaſions vindicate the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans as the trueſt ſubjects, and beſt friends to the Empire. Where they could, they obey'd active<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, where they could not, they were careful <hi>in patience to poſſeſs their ſouls.</hi> And therefore when <hi>Julian</hi> the <hi>Apoſtate</hi> urg'd his Army, moſt part made up of Chriſtians, to wicked counſels, and the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices of Idolatry, they withſtood him only with prayers and tears, becauſe (ſayes <hi>Nazianzen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Orat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> in Jul. p.</hi> 94.</note> who liv'd at that time) <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, they accounted this the only remedy in times of perſecution. Nay <hi>Julian</hi> himſelf (whom none can ſuſpect as over favourable to Chriſtians) gives them this teſtimony, that if they ſee any one mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinying againſt his Prince, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eragm. Ep. p.</hi> 528.</note> imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately they puniſh him with the ſevereſt penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:58010:11"/>
            <p>Nor were they thus ſubmiſſive and patient meerly for want of power, and becauſe they knew not how to help it; no, they could quietly dye at the Emperours command, even when they had power lying at their feet, whereof the <hi>Thebean Legion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid. Eucher. Comment. ap. Sur. Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temb.</hi> 22. <hi>&amp; prim. Chriſt. ubi ſupr. c.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 331, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> conſiſting of at leaſt ſix thouſand ſix hundred faithful and reſolute ſouldiers is a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to be forgotten inſtance; who being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by the Emperour <hi>Maximian</hi> to do ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to the gods, upon their refuſal were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to be decimated, their general <hi>Mauritius</hi> exhorting them to dye like Chriſtians, and not to oppoſe tho with power by their ſide: Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders being renewed a ſecond time, they unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly return'd this generous anſwer, <hi>We acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> Caeſar <hi>that we are your ſouldiers, and took up arms for defence of the Empire, nor did we ever betray our truſt, or forſake our ſtation, nor ſhould we ſtick now to obey your commands, did not the laws of Chriſtianity forbid us to worſhip devils, and to approach the polluted Altars of your gods. We ſee you are reſolved either to defile us with Idolatry, or to terrifie us with a decimati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; go on, Sir, as you have begun. Know, we are all Chriſtians, our bodies we ſubject to your power, but we reſerve our ſouls intire for Chriſt our Saviour. Nor is it deſpair that makes us thus reſolute againſt you, we have armes you ſee, and yet make no reſiſtance, chooſing rather to dye than to overcome, and to periſh innocent,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:58010:11"/>than to live rebellious and revengeful.</hi> Exaſperated with this invincible reſolution, the Emperour or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders a ſecond decimation, which doing no good upon them, he commanded the whole Army, Horſe and Foot to break in, who cut them off as in a moment. And thus they died with their ſwords in their hands; when being ſo many and ſo advantageouſly poſted, they might have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved their lives by force of armes, or to be ſure have ſold them at the deareſt rate. But alas, the riſing up againſt their Emperour, the propagating the faith by fire and ſword, the depoſing and aſſaſſinating Princes for the ſake of God and holy Church, were practices not more expreſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by the doctrine of the Goſpel, than they were ſtrangers to thoſe innocent and happy times. And this brings me to the third thing I propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to enquire into, and that is,</p>
            <p n="3">III. Whether any part of the Chriſtian Church at this day be juſtly guilty of this charge? And here without further preface I lay down the charge at the door of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which in this great inſtance of Religion has ſo wofully debaucht the purity and ſimplicity of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an faith that it's become now quite another thing, than what it was when it firſt came from under the hands of its Author. A Church, that in this
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:58010:12"/>regard looks more like a Council of War, or a School of the arts of Treaſon, than the Court of <hi>the Prince of peace,</hi> or the houſe of the <hi>God of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</hi> A Church, the principles of whoſe Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (as they have now modelled it) if heartily embraced, and duly improv'd to their juſt and natural tendences, are plainly inconſiſtent with the majeſty and ſecurity of Soveraign Powers, the happy government of the Civil State, and indeed with the quietneſs and good order of mankind. So true is the determination which the wiſe King <hi>James</hi> makes in this matter,
<note place="margin">Speech to both Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Parl. <hi>p.</hi> 11.</note> that as <hi>on the one part many-honeſt men ſeduc't with ſome errours of Popery may yet remain good and faithful ſubjects; ſo on the other part none of thoſe that truly know and believe the whole grounds and School-concluſions of their doctrine, can ever prove either good Chriſtians, or faithful ſubjects.</hi> But that I may not ſeem without juſt reaſon to faſten ſo heavy a charge upon them, I ſhall as briefly as I can ſhew theſe two things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>That the principles taught and belived in the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>are immediately deſtructive of the ſafety and authority of Princes, and the peace of humane ſociety.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>That the practices of the men of that Church have been all along agreeable to their prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:58010:12"/>
            <p n="1">I. The principles taught and believ'd in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> are immediately deſtructive of the ſafety and authority of Princes, and the peace of humane ſociety. And here not to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt upon their doctrine of the Popes abſolute In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibility, of the puniſhment of hereticks (whom they devote to the moſt horrid penalties, both in this and the other world) their cancelling the moſt ſolemn oaths, and that they bind no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, if diſpenc't with by the Pope, or than 'tis for the intereſt of the Catholic cauſe, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring that no faith is to be kept with heretics; their doctrine of auricular Confeſſion (whereby they ſcrew themſelves into the ſecrets of Princes) and that the moſt enormous villanies are to be concealed, if delivered under the Seal of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Binet. Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit. ap. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaub Epiſt. clxx. (ad Front. Duc.) p.</hi> 209. <hi>vid. p.</hi> 206. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> which is not to be broken up (ſay ſome of them) tho the lives of all the Kings in the World lay at ſtake; their exempting the Clergy from the juriſdiction of the Secular Powers, whereby infinite frauds, murders, and villainies are ſecurely committed; their doctrine of aequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation and mental reſervation in the moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and important caſes; their vows of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to their Superiours, whereby they are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd to attempt the moſt horrid and unnatural actions, without enquiring into the reaſon,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:58010:13"/>or boggling at the barbarity of them: all which and abundant more inſtances that might be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, ſtrike at the very vitals of peace and order among men. To paſs by alſo the blaſphemous titles, and exorbitant preheminences which their Schoolmen and Canoniſts aſcribe to the Pope, as that Kings and Emperours are his Slaves and Vaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals,
<note place="margin">See multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe cited by Dr. <hi>Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kanthorp</hi> in his Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of the Popes tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, <hi>chap.</hi> 1.</note> whom he may command &amp; caſt down at plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; that they are inferior to the meaneſt Prieſt, who is as much above a King, as a man is above a beaſt, and that as much as God Almighty excels a Prieſt, ſo much does a Prieſt excel a King. Beſides theſe, they directly maintain and teach, that the Government of the whole world both in tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals and ſpirituals is, at leaſt in order to the good of ſouls, committed to the Pope, all Regal authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty depending on him; that he may not only pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh, but deprive Kings of their Countries, and beſtow their Kingdoms upon others; that if a King be an heretic, he forfeits his title to his Crown and dignity, yea though he be but negligent to extirpate hereſie, or to execute juſtice, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the Pope may abſolve his Subjects from all duty and allegiance to him, in which caſe they are bound not to obey; that this Papal ſentence once paſs'd, he may be expell'd, or kill'd by any, yea any one of his own ſworn ſubjects may take away his life: nay, that in ſome caſes
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:58010:13"/>the people are not bound to ſtay for the Popes decree and declaration, but may of themſelves riſe up and dethrone ſuch Princes, and that they are obliged to do ſo in point of conſcience, and upon pain of their ſouls; and that ſuch proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings as theſe are agreeable to Nature, Law, Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, and the practices and precepts of holy men, and that he that doubts of it wants com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſence. All which ſcandalous and damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble propoſitions (and there are infinitely more, and ſome worſe perhaps than what I have men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned) are one or more of them <hi>in terminis</hi> main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by
<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Defenſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſid. Cath. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 23. <hi>n.</hi> 1, 16, 21. <hi>&amp; l.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 4. <hi>n.</hi> 14, 18, 19.</note> 
               <hi>Suarez,
<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>De rep. Eccleſ. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 4. § 48, 49. <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trov. Angl. p.</hi> 115, 133, 135. <hi>&amp; alib. ſaepe.</hi>
                  </note> Becanus,
<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Comment. in</hi> 1.2. <hi>Aqu. diſt.</hi> 152. §. 8. <hi>&amp; alibi.</hi>
                  </note> Vaſquez,
<note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Examen praef. monit. R. Jac. p.</hi> 49, 55, 103, 142, 143.</note> Coquaeus,
<note n="e" place="margin">Aphoriſm. Confeſſ. in verb. Clericus. prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceps. Tyrannus.</note> Emanuel Sa,
<note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>De Haereſ. c.</hi> 30. <hi>p.</hi> 293, 296.</note> Santarellus,
<note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>De Reg. &amp; Reg. inſtit. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 6. <hi>p.</hi> 58, <hi>&amp;c. c.</hi> 7. <hi>p.</hi> 63, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> Mariana,
<note n="h" place="margin">
                     <hi>Defenſ. Bell. T.</hi> 2. <hi>col.</hi> 1153, <hi>&amp;c. adv. Reg. Brit. c.</hi> 6, 7. <hi>def. Apol. Gall. p.</hi> 591.</note> Gretſer,
<note n="i" place="margin">
                     <hi>Tom.</hi> 3. <hi>diſp.</hi> 5. <hi>q.</hi> 8. <hi>punct.</hi> 3.</note> Valentia,</hi> by Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal
<note n="k" place="margin">Letter about <hi>Devent. p.</hi> 27, 28, 30. <hi>&amp; in Reſp. pro Cathol. adv. perſecut. Angl. paſſim. vid. c.</hi> 2, 4, 5. <hi>ext. in concert. Eccl. Cath. in Anglia.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Allen,
<note n="l" place="margin">
                     <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trov.</hi> 3. <hi>q.</hi> 5. <hi>artic.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 710, 711.</note> Stapleton,
<note n="m" place="margin">
                     <hi>De Viſib. Monarch. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 4. <hi>de clave David. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 6. <hi>p.</hi> 26. <hi>c.</hi> 9. <hi>p.</hi> 57. <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 10. <hi>p.</hi> 99.</note> Saunders,
<note n="n" place="margin">Quiet &amp; ſob. reck. <hi>p.</hi> 80. Letter of the Oath of Alleg. <hi>p.</hi> 18, 19, 80, 85. <hi>Philopat. (ſive ejus ſit, ſive Creſwelli) p.</hi> 106, 107. <hi>it.</hi> §. 158, 160, 162, 221.</note> Parſons,</hi> and hundreds more. I ſhall a little more particularly inſtance in <hi>Bellarmin,</hi> becauſe he is the moſt profeſt Champion of the Papal
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:58010:14"/>cauſe, and being a man of great wit and Learning expreſs'd himſelf as cautiouſly, as he well could in this matter; yea ſo cautiouſly, that Pope <hi>Sixtus</hi> V. was once reſolv'd to have condemn'd and ſuppreſt his writings, becauſe at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributing too little to the Papal authority, as the Cardinals themſelves told mine Author
<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gu. Barcl. de poteſt. Papae. edit.</hi> 1609. <hi>c.</hi> 13. <hi>p.</hi> 101. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 40. <hi>p.</hi> 329.</note>; and yet even he
<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>De Rom. Pontif. l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 6. <hi>col.</hi> 889. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 7. <hi>ib. &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> ſayes roundly, that the political Power, not only as 'tis Chriſtian but as 'tis Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, is ſubject to the Eccleſiaſtical, ſo that the Pope may in order to the good of ſouls govern and diſpoſe of temporal Princes, alter King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, take them away from one, and give them to another; that if a King be an Infidel or an Heretic (and we know what they mean by that, nay he particularly reckons the Kings of <hi>England</hi> among his inſtances) and ſeek to draw his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions to his ſect, it is not only lawful, but a duty in his ſubjects to deprive him of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. And whereas, ſayes he, the primitive Chriſtians attempted not the like on <hi>Nero, Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſian, Julian,</hi> or the reſt, it was not it ſeems that they boggled out of a ſenſe of duty, but only <hi>quia deerant vires temporales,</hi> becauſe they wanted means and power to effect it. A bold piece of falſhood,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Fuligat. vit. Bell. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 17.</note> and a ſufficient confutation of what the Writer of his Life affirms, that he could not remember that he had ever told a lye in his life,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:58010:14"/>or diſguiſed the truth by fraud or ſophiſtry. If it be here ſaid (as ſometimes they do, when pincht with theſe objections) that theſe are but the opinions of their private Doctors, and not the public and ſtanding declarations of that Church; to this I ſhall briefly return theſe three things by way of anſwer.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That this is a moſt groſs and ſenſeleſs eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the argument, for whether their Church publicly declare this or not, 'tis theſe private Doctors that ſteer mens Conſciences, conduct their practice, and that diffuſe the venom into all parts of the Chriſtian world: and if the miſchief be done by vertue of theſe helliſh Principles, Princes murdered, Kingdoms invaded, and the foundations of Government overturned, 'tis little matter whether it be done by connivence or command; as if the family be deſtroyed by the ſervants ſcattering of poyſon in every corner, 'tis but a trifling excuſe that the Maſter of the houſe did not command, but only ſtand by and ſee them do it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Theſe pernicious doctrines are publicly taught in their Schools and Univerſities, and Books of them printed in all Countries, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd, licenc't and recommended, and ſuffered to paſs without controul; the very worſt of them never cenſur'd, condemn'd, or burnt by
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:58010:15"/>the ſupream authority of that Church; which in all reaſon, juſtice, and equity they were oblig'd to do, did they not allow and own them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. (And which will fully anſwer this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) Moſt of theſe deteſtable principles are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant in the body of their <hi>Canon Law,</hi>
               <note place="margin">See the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Lincoln</hi>'s Book call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by the Church of</hi> Rome.</note> which is their public rule and ſtandard at this day; are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined in the <hi>Breves</hi> and <hi>Bulls</hi> of their ſeveral Popes, who have ſolemnly denounc't thoſe things <hi>ex Cathedra;</hi> and what's higher yet, are in effect found in the Decrees of their own General Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils: I inſtance in two: <hi>Ann.</hi> 1215. the Council of <hi>Lateran</hi> (whereat were preſent the Pope, the Patriarchs of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> ſeventy Arch-biſhops, four hundred and twelve Biſhops, eight hundred Abbots and Priors, beſides Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadors from moſt Princes in Chriſtendom, this Council) decreed, that Heretical Lords and Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers ſhould be Excommunicated; their Vaſſals abſolved from their obedience, their Lands ſeiz'd, and diſpos'd of to Catholics. In the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Council at <hi>Lyons, Ann.</hi> 1245. the Pope by advice of the Cardinals and Council, and by a definitive ſentence pronounc't there, depos'd and depriv'd the Emperour <hi>Frederic,</hi> diſcharg'd his ſworn Subjects from their Allegiance, Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicating all ſuch as ſhould obey or favour him,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:58010:15"/>commanding the Princes forthwith to proceed to a new Election: all which is inſerted into the Acts of that Council. To be ſhort, ſo evident is the caſe, that ſome of their greateſt Champi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons more candid and ingenuous than the reſt, have plainly confeſt, that if the Pope have not ſuch a power of Excommunicating and depoſing Princes, and abſolving Subjects from their Fealty and Allegiance,
<note place="margin">See Card. <hi>Perrons Harangue</hi> among his Works in French, <hi>p.</hi> 635. <hi>Leſſius (ſeu Gu. Singletonus) Diſcuſſ. Decret. Conc. Later. p.</hi> 46, 90, 100, 123. but eſpecially the Jeſuits Loyalty, prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted 1677. the firſt Treatiſe.</note> 
               <hi>their Church having all along challeng'd and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercis'd it in her ſupremeſt Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals, muſt be fallen into a dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable errour both in faith and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, and conſequently muſt ceaſe to be a true Church:</hi> that therefore the belief of it is an article eſſential to it, and <hi>to aſſert the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, is an opinion erroneous in faith, temerarious and impious.</hi> But if their Church muſt needs ſtand or fall with this principle, let them look to that; 'tis in the mean time evident enough, that the principles they believe and teach are in the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency of them immediately deſtructive of the ſafety and authority of Princes, and the peace of humane ſociety. But alas that's not all, nor the worſt of the caſe. Theſe pernicious doctrines are not meer Scholaſtic ſubtleties, dry and barren ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culations, but impregnated with life and power; and accordingly</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:58010:16"/>
            <p n="2">II. The practices of the men of that Church have been alwayes agreeable to their principles. And for the truth of this I might appeal to the Records of all Nations in Chriſtendom, thoſe volumes and Martyrologies, which the iniquity of theſe mens principles have filled with tragical and lamentable ſtories. What miſerable havoc have they made in <hi>Germany,</hi> where (to paſs by other things) the Emperour <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth was ſo perſecuted by Pope <hi>Hildebrand</hi> and his Succeſſor (with Curſes, Deprivations, Armies and Rebellions) that he was even wearied out of his life, forc't at laſt to reſign the Empire, and (tho in vain) upon his knees to beg Abſolution from the Popes Legat, and peace from his own Son, whom they had raiſed up againſt him. The ſame and worſe they did by <hi>Frederic Barbaroſſa,</hi> by <hi>Otho</hi> the Fourth, by <hi>Frederic</hi> the Second, and by <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh, who marching with an Army into <hi>Italy</hi> to recover the Rights of the Empire, is very credibly reported
<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sabell. Ennead. ix. l.</hi> 8. <hi>p.</hi> 794. <hi>Plat. in Clem.</hi> v. <hi>p.</hi> 252. <hi>Naucler. Chron. Gen.</hi> xliv. <hi>p.</hi> 372. <hi>Volater. l.</hi> 23. <hi>p.</hi> 879. <hi>Genebr. Chron. l.</hi> 4. <hi>Ann.</hi> 1305. <hi>p.</hi> 677.</note> to have been poyſon'd with the Sacrament. Nor did the Emperours en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy any tolerable quiet from <hi>Rome,</hi> till <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth heartily eſpous'd the Papal intereſt, ever ſince whoſe time the Emperours have been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:58010:16"/>intirely ſwayed by the Councils of the <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits.</hi> An order of men born for the deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of mankind, whom therefore the wiſe State of <hi>Venice</hi> baniſht out of all their Dominions,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hiſtor. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terdict. Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net. l.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 71. <hi>Eng. Edit. p.</hi> 138.</note> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing they did it for this reaſon, becauſe they had been the authors and inſtruments of all up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roars, ſeditions, confuſions, and ruines that had hapned in thoſe times in all the Kingdoms and States of the Chriſtian world. To which let me add what their Martyr <hi>Campian</hi> (who was hang'd at <hi>Tyburn)</hi> expreſly tells us,
<note place="margin">Epiſt. ad Concil. Reg. Angl. x. ejus Rat. praefix. in Concert. Cath. &amp; alib.</note> that all the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> in the world have long ſince entred into Covenant, never to ceaſe their attempts upon us, which they deſpair not to take effect, ſo long as any one <hi>Jeſuite</hi> remains in the world.</p>
            <p>In <hi>France</hi> the poyſon of theſe principles has wrought no leſs vigorouſly and effectually: Pope <hi>Zachary</hi> depos'd <hi>Childeric</hi> III. who was thereupon thruſt into a Monaſtery, and the Pope beſtowed the Crown upon <hi>Pipin</hi> the <hi>Major-domo</hi> of his Palace. <hi>Lewis</hi> VII. was interdicted, and forc't to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit. <hi>Philip</hi> the Fourth ſo vext with the oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Pope <hi>Boniface</hi> the Eighth, that for three years together he ſcarce had one quiet hour. After the Reformation the Zeal of Popery grew more fierce and bloody. In the <hi>Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian</hi> Maſſacre were ſlain there and in other parts of <hi>France</hi> to the number of above thirty thouſand
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:58010:17"/>Proteſtants. The news whereof arriving at <hi>Rome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Thuan. lib.</hi> 53. <hi>ad Ann.</hi> 1572. <hi>Tom.</hi> 11. <hi>p.</hi> 837.</note> the Pope preſently convened the Cardinals, and went in a ſolemn proceſſion to S. <hi>Mark</hi>'s Church, there to give public thanks to God for ſo great a bleſſing conferr'd upon the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Chriſtian world, and reſolved for this reaſon chiefly that the year of <hi>Jubilee</hi> ſhould be immediately proclaimed, that all Chriſtendom might rejoice for ſo great a ſlaughter of heretics: and the whole ſolemnity was concluded with ſhooting off the Great Guns, Bonefires, and all other expreſſions of the greateſt triumph and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing. What miſerable ruins, ſlaughters, and devaſtations were made by the confederates of the <hi>Holy League</hi> for many years together? And in the midſt of all, <hi>Henry</hi> the Third, a Prince of their own Communion, ſtab'd by <hi>Jaques Clement,</hi> a <hi>Dominican</hi> Frier, encouraged thereunto by the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> and particularly by his Father Confeſſour, who promiſed him a Crown of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdom, if he died in the attempt, but if he ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vived, that he ſhould be made a Biſhop or a Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Boucherius de fuſta Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatione Henrici III. edit. Lugd. An.</hi> 1591. <hi>Franc. Veron. Apol. pour Jehan Chaſtel. alii<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> vid. Thuan ad An.</hi> 1589. <hi>T.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 460. <hi>&amp; An.</hi> 1594. <hi>T.</hi> 5. <hi>p.</hi> 519. <hi>Ann.</hi> 1604. <hi>p.</hi> 1124.</note> And the fact magnified as noble and hero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ick, juſtified in Printed Apologies, and Books writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten on purpoſe to prove, that 'tis lawful ſo a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate man to kill a Tyrant, though there be neither
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:58010:17"/>ſentence of the Church nor Kingdom pronounc't againſt him.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Orat. Sixti</hi> V. <hi>habita Sept.</hi> 11. 1589. prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted firſt at <hi>Rome,</hi> then at <hi>Paris, An.</hi> 1589. by Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Holy Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and approbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of three <hi>Sorbon</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, and ſince oft Reprinted, <hi>vid. Thu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an. ib. An.</hi> 1589.</note> Nay 'twas approv'd and applauded by Pope <hi>Sixtus</hi> V. in an Oration made on purpoſe in the Conſiſtory, wherein he compares it to, and prefers it before that of <hi>Judith</hi>'s killing <hi>Holofernes,</hi> and more than once and again affirms, that that great and miraculous work was to be aſcrib'd on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the particular Providence of God, without whoſe eſpecial aid, he ſayes, it could not have been brought to paſs. The like unhappy fate overtook his Succeſſour, the great King <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth, whom <hi>Ravaillac</hi> (who had ſometimes been a Monk) ſtab'd in his Coach with a poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned knife, and at his Examination boldly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs'd he did it, becauſe the King did not take Arms againſt the <hi>Hugonots,</hi> and that his making War againſt the Pope, is the ſame as to make War againſt God, <hi>Seeing the Pope was God, and God was the Pope.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Twere endleſs to purſue the ſtories of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Nations: and happy had it been for us, had they kept there. But tho nature ſeems to have ſecur'd us pretty well againſt external invaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, yet theſe reſtleſs and daring men after all the villanies they have done in other Countreys, have put their helliſh deſigns aboard, and <hi>are come hither alſo.</hi> I paſs over their infinite Treaſons, Diſturbances, and Rebellions, precedent to the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:58010:18"/>Reformation. No ſooner had <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth thrown off the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Yoke, but a <hi>Bull</hi> of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication was thundred out againſt him, and that followed by no leſs than three Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons at home, contrived and carried on by the counſels and artifice of the Popiſh Clergy; and little leſs there were in the ſhort Reign of his Succeſſor. In the long and happy Reign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid. Camb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den. Annal. Elizab. ad Ann.</hi> 1569, 1570, —79, —80, —83, —84, —85, —86, —87, —88, —94, —98. Biſhop <hi>Carleton</hi>'s Thankful Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of God's mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, <hi>per tot. Foulis</hi> Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, <hi>&amp;c. l.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 3, 4, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> few years paſs'd over her head without ſome conſiderable attempt either againſt her life or Government: <hi>Ann.</hi> 1569. came out <hi>Pius</hi> V. his <hi>Bull</hi> of deprivation againſt her, whereupon ſucceeded two Rebellions in the North, the chief whereof was headed by the Earls of <hi>Weſtmorland</hi> and <hi>Northumberland.</hi> The next year <hi>Stuckley</hi> by the help of the <hi>Pope</hi> and <hi>Spaniard</hi> invaded <hi>Ireland,</hi> where <hi>Saunders</hi> the <hi>Jeſuit,</hi> the firebrand of that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, for want of ſucceſs fell mad and died. This was not well over, when <hi>Campian</hi> and <hi>Parſons</hi> came hither, the two firſt <hi>Jeſuits</hi> (would God they had been the laſt) that ever arriv'd in <hi>England,</hi> who ſet themſelves to blow up the Nation into an open flame. Two years after <hi>Somervile</hi> inflam'd by the Writings of the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> crowded with a drawn Sword into the Queens preſence, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſet upon one or two that ſtood in his way, confeſt 'twas his intent to have murdered the Queen, and for fear of telling more tales, was
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:58010:18"/>three dayes after found ſtrangled in priſon. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the ſame time <hi>Throgmorton</hi> and ſome others conſpired againſt her, with deſign to ſet up the Queen of <hi>Scots. Ann.</hi> 1585. <hi>William Parry</hi> Doctor of Law, ſet on by the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> the Popes <hi>Nuncio,</hi> and by the Pope himſelf, undertook to kill the Queen, but his heart failing in the attempt, he was taken and Executed. The year after <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bington</hi> and his accomplices held a conſult at S. <hi>Giles in the Fields</hi> to murder the Queen, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade the Realm, for which ſeven of them were hang'd; and the like plotted by <hi>Stafford</hi> and others the following year. In eighty eight was the famous, but unſucceſsful Invaſion of the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible Armado.</hi> In ninety three Dr. <hi>Lopez</hi> a <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuguez,</hi> the Queen's Phyſitian, was hired for fifty thouſand Crowns to poyſon her, which he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt afterwards. In ninety ſix <hi>Edw. Squire</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing inſtructed in <hi>Spain</hi> by <hi>Walpool</hi> the <hi>Jeſuit,</hi> and by him furniſht with poyſon prepared on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, undertook to poyſon the Queen's Saddle, which he did, tho through the goodneſs of the Divine Providence it took no effect.</p>
            <p>King <hi>James</hi> ſucceeded to the Crown, and as an entail to that, to the hatred and malice of the Popiſh party. To prepare the way, <hi>Parſons</hi> the <hi>Jeſuite</hi> writes a Book of the Succeſſion to prove that he had no juſt title to the Crown; and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:58010:19"/>
               <hi>Garnet</hi> another of that Order procur'd two ſeveral <hi>Breves</hi> from <hi>Rome</hi> to exclude him,
<note place="margin">See Sr. <hi>Edw. Cook</hi>'s Speech at <hi>Garnet</hi>'s trial. Relat. of the <hi>Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powd. Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, p.</hi> 159. and <hi>Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net</hi>'s Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſ. at his Execut. <hi>p.</hi> 226.</note> or any of the next line, unleſs they were <hi>Roman</hi> Catholics; <hi>Watſon</hi> and <hi>Clark,</hi> two Secular Prieſts drew ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of the Nobility and Gentry into a Combina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (which they ſeal'd with an Oath of Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy) to ſurprize the King and the Prince, and to force from him a toleration of their Religion for which they were Executed. And now ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly deſpairing of any favour from that wiſe and learned Prince, theſe <hi>malignant and deviliſh Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>An.</hi> 3 <hi>Jac. R. c.</hi> 1.</note> Jeſuites, and Seminary Prieſts,</hi> (as they are call'd in the very words of the Act of Parliament for the obſervation of this day) entred into a black and unparallel'd conſpiracy, the <hi>Powder-Treaſon</hi> (the deliverance from which we ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly celebrate at this time) wherein fire and darkneſs were ſummon'd up from hell to mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to the Execution, and no leſs than King and Kingdom, Religion and Liberty, Eſtates and Lives deſign'd at once as a Burnt-ſacrifice to their rage and fury.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.4.</note> 
               <hi>But he that ſits in heaven did laugh, the Lord had them in deriſion,</hi> over-rul'd the Plots, and <hi>diſappointed the devices of the crafty,
<note place="margin">Job 5.12.</note> ſo that their hands could not perform their enterprize.</hi> In the Reign of King <hi>Charles</hi> I. they ſtill carried on the ſame deſign, and after all, a <hi>Jeſuitical</hi> Plot was ſet on foot (diſcovered by means of <hi>Andreas ab Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernfield)</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:58010:19"/>to murder the Arch-biſhop,
<note place="margin">Printed in <hi>Pryn</hi>'s <hi>Romes Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter piece. An.</hi> 1643.</note> and take away the King's Life. Their bloody and inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane butcheries in <hi>Ireland,</hi> (wherein above 100000 Proteſtants were barbarouſly murdered in cool blood) are known to all. What hand they had in the troubles of this and the neighbour Nation, how they voted at their conſults,
<note place="margin">See Dr. <hi>Pet. du Moulins</hi> Vindicat. of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt. Relig. <hi>ch.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 58. and his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply to a Perſon of honour, <hi>p.</hi> 4, 5, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and the truth of the charge more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly cleared in ſome pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per (which I have read) of Dr. <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grave</hi> late Prebend of <hi>Canterbury.</hi>
               </note> 'twas for the intereſt of the Catholick Cauſe, that the King ſhould dye, how active and inſtrumental they were to promote the Councils that took away the life of that excellent Prince, the world is not now to learn. And have they dealt bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with us in the Reign of his Succeſſour, the King that now is? To omit all other taſtes they have given us of their good will, their horrid conſpiracy at this day (whereat we all ſtand amaz'd and tremble) contriv'd and carried on with ſo inhumane and barbarous a deſign, is a ſufficient evidence. A Plot tho later in time, not inferiour in malignity to any of the reſt; and ſo much the worſe, becauſe done againſt all the laws of kindneſs and gratitude, at a time when the public rods and axes were laid aſleep, and they liv'd ſecure and undiſturb'd under the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful connivance of the Government.</p>
            <p>And tell me now after all this whether diſloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty and Treaſon, blood and villany be not in a manner incorporated into the preſent polity
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:58010:20"/>and conſtitution of the See of <hi>Rome;</hi> and as Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians ſay of old <hi>Rome,</hi> that the foundations of it were laid in blood, ſo whether <hi>Rome</hi> at this day be not built up, cemented, and ſupported by the ſame bloody arts and methods. A conſtitution, that with <hi>Saul</hi> purſues its enemies to rage and madneſs, and breaths out nothing but threatning and ſlaughter againſt any that oppoſe it. 'Twas the happy character of the Chriſtian Religion, that of old dropt from the pen of an Heathen, <hi>nil niſi juſtum ſuadet &amp; lene,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Am. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellin. l.</hi> 22. <hi>p.</hi> 1626.</note> that it commands no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but what's juſt, mild and gentle; whereas now were an unbiaſt Pagan to take the meaſures of Chriſtianity from what is ordinarily allowed and practis'd in the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, he would un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly proſcribe it not only as a ſcene of child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Pageantry, but as a piece of the moſt exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite ſavageneſs and barbarity. In ſhort, they are a race of men, who (as our Church truly ſayes in the Collect for this day) <hi>turn Religion into Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, and faith into faction,</hi> and who have manag'd the cauſe of the beſt Religion in the world with the utmoſt advantages both of ſcandal to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, and of miſchief to the world.</p>
            <p>I could not pardon my ſelf, if upon ſo fair an occaſion I ſhould not make this further inference, that if Popery be ſo foul and odious a charge, we would be very cautious upon whom we faſten
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:58010:20"/>that deteſtable character of <hi>Papiſts,</hi> or <hi>Popiſhly-af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected;</hi> leſt we would the righteous with the wicked, and abuſe innocent and undeſerving men, for no other reaſon perhaps, than becauſe in ſome few little things they are not of our mind. Were <hi>Cramner</hi> and <hi>Ridley,</hi> were <hi>Hooper</hi> and <hi>Latimer,</hi> were theſe men Papiſts? if not, I beſeech you let not any be traduc't under that odious name, that act by the ſame principles, and are ready to ſuffer for the ſame cauſe that they did. 'Tis time to lay aſide our feuds and quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels, and unanimouſly to ſet our ſelves againſt the common enemy, when <hi>Hannibal ad portas,</hi> there's an Enemy at the Gates, that ſeeks to do his work with our hands, and would then rejoice in the ruine of us both. Let us heartily join in a grateful commemoration of this dayes delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and pay our utmoſt thanks to heaven for a mercy, that preſerv'd us a free and unenſlaved Nation, and which is more, preſerved the Goſpel to us, which is the glory of a Nation. Conſider, with what ſubtlety and arts of ſecrecy this work of darkneſs was carried on: 'twas a myſtery of iniquity, to unravel the labyrinths whereof were a task fitter for a Secretary of the Prince of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Nothing of malice or miſchief appear'd above ground, no demonſtrations of turbulency or diſcontent, but all went mask'd under a
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:58010:21"/>ſmooth brow;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>M. Sen. Controv.</hi> 22. <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 218.</note> that as he in <hi>Seneca, non ante intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexit proditionem, quàm proditus ſit,</hi> he was in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner betray'd, before he underſtood the Treaſon; ſo here, the deſign was to take effect in a way, wherein human force and policy ſhould be too late to make reſiſtance, and they who acted it ſhould only ſtand behind the Curtain: this being part of that very Letter, (which through the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of God proved the means of its diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry) <hi>that tho there ſhould be no appearance of any ſtir, yet they ſhould receive a terrible blow, and none ſee who hurt them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, Conſider the infinite horrour and vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lany of the deſign; a deſign that ſtruck at the very vitals of the Kingdom, the liberty of the people, the glory and purity of Religion, the life, honour, and happineſs of King, Prince, Peers, and the repreſentative commonalty of the Nation all at once. This was no petty wickedneſs, 'twas a monſter of Conſpiracy (as the great <hi>Thuanus</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuouſly confeſſes) whereto no age or Nation ever brought forth a parallel.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ad Ann.</hi> 1606. <hi>lib.</hi> 135. <hi>T.</hi> 5. <hi>p.</hi> 1215.</note> Nothing would ſerve their turns, unleſs Kings and Princes (whoſe lives have been alwayes even by the moſt barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Nations held Sacred and Venerable) and the whole beauty and glory of ſuch a flouriſhing Church and Nation at once fell before them, and that too by the moſt mercileſs and raging Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:58010:21"/>and with ſuch unheard of circumſtances of inhumanity, that nothing but the wit of hell could have found them out. <hi>Curſed be their anger, for it was fierce, and their wrath, for it was cruel; may God for ever divide them in Jacob, and ſcatter them in Iſrael:</hi> may that Almighty wiſdom, power, and goodneſs, that has hitherto ſuperintended the happineſs and ſecurity of this Nation, evermore blaſt and thunder-ſtrike their plots and projects, and turn the Counſels of all ſuch <hi>Achitophels</hi> into fooliſhneſs: that <hi>all men may fear,
<note place="margin">Pſalm 64.9, 10.</note> and declare the work of God, and wiſely conſider of his doing; that the righteous may be glad in the Lord, and truſt in him, and all the upright in heart may glory;</hi> while <hi>the Lord is known by the judgement which he executeth,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 9.16.</note> and the wicked is ſnared in the work of his own hands.</hi> Which God of his infinite mercy grant for <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> ſake. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
